Guide to the Boone and Crockett Club Records circa 1885-2009
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Boone and Crockett Club records
circa 1885-2009
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 738
Boone and Crockett Club
125.7 linear feet
This collection consists of the records of the Boone and Crockett Club which was founded in 1887 by Theodore Roosevelt and George Bird Grinnell and remains active today. Since its inception the Club has championed conservation causes and legislation, hunter ethics, and North American big game records keeping.
Historical Note
In December 1887, a dinner was held by Theodore Roosevelt at his home in New York City and was attended by 10 of his friends, all hunting enthusiasts. Among the attendees were Dr. George Bird Grinnell, then editor of Field and Stream magazine, Roosevelt’s cousin, and Roosevelt’s brother. At the dinner Theodore Roosevelt proposed that the guests form an organization to promote sport with the rifle and work for the preservation of the large game of North America.
The first formal meeting of the Boone and Crockett Club was held in February 1888. Those present elected Theodore Roosevelt as President of the Club. The administrative duties of the Club would fall to an Executive Committee and Executive Officers. An editorial committee, with George Bird Grinnell as chair, was formed to prepare publications that promoted the Club’s conservation message. American Big-Game Hunting, by George Bird Grinnell and Theodore Roosevelt, was the first volume published by the Club and was released in October of 1893 by Forest and Stream Publishing Company. This volume was followed by several more game-related publications in collaboration with Forest and Stream Publishing Company.
A Committee on Admissions was formed at the Club’s first meeting. Membership was to be kept to 100 in order to keep administrative work to a minimum so that officers could be free to use their time for the goals of the Club. It was decided that regular membership requirements included killing “in fair chase” one specimen of three species of the larger game mammals of North America. Associate memberships were conferred upon men who did not meet these requirements but were prominent members of the hunting and conservation community. Another committee was appointed “to promote useful and proper legislation toward the enlargement and better management of Yellowstone National Park.” This committee, along with additional Club members, was instrumental in the passage of the Yellowstone Park Protective Act of 1895.
In 1910, a Game Preservation Committee was appointed with George Bird Grinnell as chair. This committee lent its support to the passage of conservation laws and policies such as the Alaska Game Law, the establishment of Glacier and Mt. McKinley National Parks, a bill to enlarge Yellowstone National Park, and many forest reserve and game refuge bills. The Club was able to lend effective support to conservation efforts due to its number of notable members, including Aldo Leopold, Gifford Pinchot, Theodore Roosevelt, Grinnell, Charles Sheldon, John F. Lacey, Stephen Mather, Jay N. “Ding” Darling, and many other prominent conservationists.
Between the years 1906 and 1922, Club member William T. Hornaday began collecting and cataloging exceptional big game heads. This collection became the National Collection of Heads and Horns and was displayed at the Bronx Zoo in New York City beginning in 1922. The Club assumed ownership of the National Collection of Heads and Horns in 1978 and the collection is currently available for viewing at the Buffalo Bill Historical Center in Cody, Wyoming.
The National Collection of Heads and Horns and the early conservation efforts of the Club sparked an interest in some members for big game records keeping. In the early 1930s, the Boone and Crockett Club began to assemble data on the maximum size attained by various species of North American big game. Prentiss N. Gray published the Club’s first big game records book titled Records of North American Big Game in conjunction with the National Collection of Heads and Horns in 1932. A second edition followed in 1939. These editions marked the first time that North American big game records were collected, authenticated, and published.
In 1947, the Club formed a Conservation Committee under the chairmanship of Richard Borden of the National Wildlife Federation. The Conservation Committee endorsed bills and produced policy statements for conservation, and was instrumental in saving the Florida Key Deer from extinction and establishing a Key Deer refuge in 1957. The Club also began supporting big game research through small monetary grants in 1948. Through oversight of the Conservation Committee, the Club contributed to numerous wildlife research projects including predator-prey relationships in Alaska, moose-wolf relationships on Isle Royale National Park, research on grizzly bears in Yellowstone National Park, and many others. In 1972, the Conservation Committee established an official Grant-in-Aid Subcommittee to oversee grant proposals. The Grant-in-Aid program continues today as the William I. Spencer Conservation Grants Program. The program is supported by endowments named for William I. Spencer and Tim Hixon.
In 1947, the Club held their first annual Big Game Competition. Supervision of the Competition was the responsibility of the Boone and Crockett Club’s Records of North American Big Game Committee, which was established in 1935. Winners were chosen by a judges’ panel based on skull length, antler or horn length, and basal circumference. The popularity of the competition and the records books led the Club to consider establishing an objective scoring system that could be used by trophy holders to measure their own specimens. In 1949, the Club appointed a committee, chaired by longtime Club member Samuel B. Webb, to develop the Official Scoring System for North American Big Game Trophies. In 1950, the system was adopted by the Club and soon became the standard for measuring North American big game. With the new scoring system in place, the Boone and Crockett Club remeasured the trophies in every category originally published in North American Big Game and published the results in a new edition records book in 1952. The system proved to be so effective it is still in use today in essentially the same form.
Editions of Records of North American Big Game were published every six to seven years after 1952 and 1993, when it was determined that records books would be published every six years. In addition to the original records books, the Club has published volumes on record elk, mule deer and whitetail deer. With collaborative oversight by Club-appointed committees and professional staff, the Boone and Crockett Club continues to publish books about hunting and conservation.
After the success of the initial Big Game Competition, the Boone and Crockett Club continued to hold annual Competitions until 1952, when competitions moved to every 2 years. In 1968, the Club moved the competitions to every three years. After the 14th North American Big Game Competition, held in 1971, the Club chose to change the name of their records program contests to the North American Big Game Awards to deemphasize the competition aspect of trophy hunting.
In 1973, the Boone and Crockett Club began collaborating with the National Rifle Association to sponsor records keeping. The tri-annual North American Big Game Awards Program was run from the Hunting Activities Department of the National Rifle Association by wildlife biologist William H. Nesbitt. The Hunting Activities Department was also responsible for processing entries into the Awards Programs and general records keeping. The Records of North American Big Game Committee of the Boone and Crockett Club retained responsibility for the polices of records keeping, including fair chase requirements, boundary identification, minimum scores, and species to include in the Awards Programs.
In December 1980, the collaboration with the National Rifle Association was dissolved and the Club assumed sole responsibility for the North American Big Game Awards Programs. In January 1981, the Club appointed William H. Nesbitt as Administrative Director for the Boone and Crockett Club’s Big Game Records program to work collaboratively with the Records of North American Big Game Committee. Currently, the administrative duties of Big Game Records are still shared by professional staff and the Records of North American Big Game Committee.
In 1985, with the help of a loan from The Nature Conservancy, the Boone and Crockett Club purchased the Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Ranch, located 10 miles southwest of Dupuyer, Montana on the Rocky Mountain Front, adjacent to the Bob Marshall Wilderness and Blackleaf Wildlife Management Area. The Boone and Crockett Foundation was formed and charged with managing and directing the Ranch, which the Club uses to conduct habitat research, conservation education programs, and land management demonstrations. In 2001, the Club completed construction of the Elmer E. Rasmuson Wildlife Conservation Center at the Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Ranch. The Center serves as a headquarters for the Club’s Lee and Penny Anderson Conservation Education Program, which offers education programs for people of all ages.
In 1986, the Boone and Crockett Club began publication of an Associates Newsletter which contained hunting and conservation articles and was distributed to Associate Members. This newsletter gave rise to the Club magazine Fair Chase in 1994. Fair Chase continues to be published quarterly and distributed to Associate Members of the Club.
In May of 1987, the Club entered into collaboration with The University of Montana to establish and direct research programs on the Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Ranch. Additionally, a Boone and Crockett Wildlife professorship was established at the university. In late 1990, the Club formed a hiring committee for the professorship and in 1992 Hal Salwasser was hired as the first Boone and Crockett Professor of Wildlife Conservation. In addition to the collaboration with The University of Montana, the Club currently has affiliated programs at Texas A&M, Oregon State University, and Michigan State University. In 2009, all physical assets, including the Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Ranch, were transferred from the Boone and Crockett Foundation to the Boone and Crockett Club. Although the Foundation no longer plays a role in the day-to-day management of the Ranch, the Foundation continues to raise funds to support and endow conservation education programs.
In 1992, the Boone and Crockett Club purchased the historic Old Milwaukee Railroad Depot on the Clark Fork River in Missoula, Montana, and relocated its headquarters there from Dumfries, Virginia. The Club continues to support its original mission of conservation and game preservation.
The Boone and Crockett Club Records have been divided into six Series, most of which have been further subdivided. The largest series in this collection is Series I: Administration, which contains early administrative correspondence and Executive Committee minutes, almost an entire run of the minutes of the Club’s annual meetings which began in 1893, and an almost complete run of Officer, Committee, and Membership booklets which were produced by the Club each year.
This collection also includes materials documenting the Club’s involvement in the big game conservation history of North America including general correspondence, Game Preservation Committee and Conservation Committee meeting minutes and correspondence, and materials documenting the Boone and Crockett Club’s Conservation Grants Program. The collection also contains materials that relate to the Boone and Crockett Club’s big game records keeping activities. These materials include documents pertaining to North American Big Game Records Competitions and Awards Programs, Records of North American Big Game Committee meeting minutes and correspondence files, the materials produced by the administrative staff of the Club’s Big Game Records Division, and materials related to the National Collection of Heads and Horns. Additionally, the records include documents related to the Boone and Crockett Club’s publications including administrative correspondence, planning materials and drafts of the Club’s records books, and drafts and correspondence related to the Club’s Fair Chase magazine.
This collection has been arranged in 6 series: Adminstration, Conservation, Big Game Records, Communication, Foundation, and Audio and Video Materials. Each series has subseries, and several have sub-subseries as noted below:
Series I: Administration, 1888-2007, 45.5 linear feet
Subseries 1: Constitution, By-Laws, and Incorporation, 1902-1993, 0.5 linear feet
Subseries 2: Correspondence, 1891-1998, 5.75 linear feet
Subseries 3: Financial and Legal Materials, 1892-1998, 6.0 linear feet
Subseries 4: Officers and Committees, 1888-2005, 14.75 linear feet
Sub-subseries 1: Officers’ Correspondence and Reports, 1894-1999, 5.75 linear feet
Sub-subseries 2: Executive Committee and Board of Directors, 1888-2005, 8.5 linear feet
Sub-subseries 3: Other Administrative Committees, 1950-2005, 0.5 linear feet
Subseries 5: Member Meetings, 1894-2007, 5.75 linear feet
Sub-subseries 1: Annual Meetings and Dinners, 1894-2007, 3.75 linear feet
Sub-subseries 2: Centennial Celebration, 1982-1989, 0.5 linear feet
Sub-subseries 3: Other Member Meetings, 1902-2003, 1.5 linear feet
Subseries 6: Membership, 1899-2007, 6.5 linear feet
Subseries 7: Library, 1960-1984, 0.5 linear feet
Subseries 8: Physical Assets, 1910-2002, 2.75 linear feet
Subseries 9: History, 1912-1999, 0.75 linear feet
Subseries 10: Speeches and Dedications, 1919-1975, 0.125 linear feet
Subseries 11: Office Administration, 1958-1995, 1.375
Sub-subseries 1: General Materials, 1958-1995, 0.875 linear feet
Sub-subseries 2: Staff Correspondence, 1968-1992, 0.5 linear feet
Subseries 12: Miscellaneous, 1897-2000, 0.75 linear feet
Series II: Conservation, 1902-2001, 21.5 linear feet
Subseries 1: Early Conservation Efforts, 1902-1955, 1.0 linear foot
Subseries 2: Conservation Committee, 1933-2001, 17.875 linear feet
Sub-subseries 1: Correspondence, Meeting Minutes, and Reports, 1945-1999, 4.375 linear feet
Sub-subseries 2: Conservation Grants Program, 1933-2001, 10.75 linear feet
Sub-subseries 2.1: Conservation Grants - 2011 Accession, 1973-2001, 9.5 linear feet
Sub-subseries 3: Conferences, Workshops, and Collaborations, 1958-2000, 2.0 linear feet
Sub-subseries 4: Subject Files and Other Materials, 1947-2000, 0.75 linear feet
Subseries 3: Fair Chase and Other Positions, 1959-2001, 1.0 linear foot
Subseries 4: Conservation Awards, 1983-1995, 0.375 linear feet
Subseries 5: Campaigns, 1982-1996, 1.25 linear feet
Series III: Big Game Records, 1906-2002, 30.0 linear feet
Subseries 1: Administration, 1931-1999, 17.50 linear feet
Sub-subseries 1: Committees, 1931-1999, 11.50 linear feet
Sub-sub-subseries 1: Records of North American Big Game Committee, 1931- 1999, 10.75 linear feet
Sub-sub-subseries 2: Friends of North American Big Game Committee, 1947- 1964, 0.5 linear feet
Sub-sub-subseries 3: Other Committees, 1949-1974, 0.25 linear feet
Sub-subseries 2: North American Big Game Awards Program, 1965-1986, 3.0 linear feet
Sub-subseries 3: Professional Staff, 1975-1997, 3.0 linear feet
Subseries 2: Awards Competitions and Programs, 1947-2001, 8.0 linear feet
Subseries 3: Sagamore Hill Medal Program, 1948-1993, 0.25 linear feet
Subseries 4: Official Measurer Materials, 1957-1998, 1.5 linear feet
Subseries 5: National Collection of Heads and Horns, 1906-2002, 2.75 linear feet
Series IV: Communications, 1904-2009, 18.0 linear feet
Subseries 1: Publications, 1910-2009, 15.375 linear feet
Sub-subseries 1: Administration, 1910-2000, 3.75 linear feet
Sub-subseries 2: Books, 1932-2001, 9.50 linear feet
Sub-sub-subseries 1: Records of North American Big Game Books, 1932-1994, 6.75 linear feet
Sub-sub-subseries 2: Other Books, 1954-2001, 2.75 linear feet
Sub-subseries 3: Fair Chase Magazine, 1980-2009, 1.5 linear feet
Sub-subseries 4: Newsletters, 1983-2001, 0.375 linear feet
Sub-subseries 5: Miscellaneous Publications, 1911-1988, 0.25 linear feet
Subseries 2: Associates Program, 1976-1996, 1.25 linear feet
Subseries 3: Licensing, Trademarks, Copyrights, Advertisements, and Publicity, 1904-2006, 1.125 linear feet
Subseries 4: Films and Miscellaneous Materials, 1969-1995, 0.25 linear feet
Series V: Foundation, 1982-2005, 9.5 linear feet
Subseries 1: Board of Directors Materials, 1985-1994, 0.5 linear feet
Subseries 2: Correspondence, 1984-2002, 2.0 linear feet
Subseries 3: Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Ranch, 1982-2005, 3.25 linear feet
Subseries 4: University of Montana Applied Research Program and Professorship, 1985-1996, 0.5 linear feet
Subseries 5: Financial and Fundraising, 1983-1998, 3.0 linear feet
Subseries 6: Miscellaneous, 1986-1991, 0.25 linear feet
Series VI: Unprocessed Audio and Video Material, undated, 3.0 linear feet
Series VII: George Bird Grinnell Manuscripts, circa 1885-1910, 0.2 linear feet
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula. Grants with social security numbers are restricted. Records created 10 years ago or less are fully restricted.
The majority of these records were held by the Boone and Crockett Club at their headquarters in Missoula, Montana, until their transfer to Archives & Special Collections. A small box of early minutes and letters was deposited at the Archives in 1992. The bulk of the collection was donated in March of 2009. An addition to the Club's records was donated in 2011. A small collection of manuscripts, most by George Bird Grinnell, was added in 2017.
These records were transferred by the Boone and Crockett Club to the Archives in 1992. 2009 and 2011.
Additional records of enduring value will be transferred from Club headquarters as they become inactive.
Philip L. Wright's papers related to his work as an official measurer for the Boone and Crockett Club were housed at Club headquarters and transferred to Archives and Special Collections along with the other Boone and Crockett Club materials in 2009. The Wright papers have been arranged as collection Mss 781.
Trefethen, James B. An American Crusade for Wildlife
Two small collections of the Boone and Crockett Club’s records exist at the Carnegie Museum of Natural History in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania and at the American Museum of Natural History in New York City, New York. Archives and Special Collections at the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library holds a collection of 58 oral histories generated by the Club (OH 297).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919
National Collection of Heads and Horns (U.S.)
Big game hunting--North America--Societies, etc.; Game protection--North America--Societies, etc.; Hunting--Moral and ethical aspects; Hunting trophies--North America; Hunting trophies--North America--Statistics; Sports officiating--North America; Wildlife conservation--Law and legislation--United States; Wildlife conservation--North America--Societies, etc.
Montana; Fisheries and Wildlife; Sports and Recreation
Fair chase
- Administration, 1888-2007; Series I; 45.5 linear feet
  This series contains materials related to the administrative division of the Boone and Crockett Club, including general correspondence, officer and committee reports, meeting minutes, and materials related to the Club’s annual and other member meetings. The Series has been divided into twelve subseries, most of which have been subdivided further into sub-subseries.
  Materials were grouped and interfiled by the processor to reflect the historic and current organization of the Club’s administration. Series are arranged alphabetically.
  - Constitution, By-laws and Incorporation, 1902-1993; Subseries 1; 0.5 linear feet
    This subseries contains drafts of the Club’s constitution, by-laws, and incorporation. It documents the evolution of the Club’s by-laws as it contains correspondence regarding amendments and proposed changes dating from 1922 through 1993. Additionally, the series contains drafts and proposed amendments of the Club’s constitution and documents the evolution of the Club’s statement of purpose.
    - Articles of Incorporation, Annual Registration Fee Assessment and Report, 1978-1991 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - By-Laws, 1923 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - By-Laws Amendments, 1922-1931 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - By-Laws Amendments, 1948-1959 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - By-Laws Amendments, 1969-1976 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - By-Laws and Charter Amendments, Correspondence and Memoranda, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - By-laws Amendments, Correspondence and Memoranda, 1988 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - By-laws Amendments, Correspondence, 1989 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - By-Laws, Originals, 1993 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Certificate of Incorporation, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Constitution, 1902 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Constitution, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Constitution, Correspondence and Drafts, 1904 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Constitution, Proposed Amendment, undated (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Incorporation, Correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Incorporation, Meeting Minutes and Proposal, 1931 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Incorporation, Subcommittee Report, 1923 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Statement of Purpose, 1957-1975 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Statement of Purpose, Correspondence, Drafts, and Memoranda, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Correspondence, 1891-1998; Subseries 2; 5.75 linear feet
    This subseries contains a run of general correspondence that documents the grassroots development of the Club. Although correspondence before 1891 that would document the founding of the Club is missing from the collection, early incoming and outgoing correspondence by founding Club members George Bird Grinnell and Theodore Roosevelt is included in this subseries. Additionally, the subseries contains materials that document the Club’s organizational development. Although this early correspondence does document the Club’s involvement in conservation and publications, specific correspondence regarding these subjects and big game records can be found in Series’ II, III, and IV.
    - American Museum of Natural History, Hall of American Mammals, Correspondence, 1931-1941 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - American Museum of Natural History, Hall of North American Mammals, Alaskan Brown Bear Group, Correspondence, 1937-1940 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - American Museum of Natural History, Correspondence, 1973-1978 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - American Museum of Natural History, Correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Daniel M. Barringer, Correspondence, 1928 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Daniel Boone and Davy Crockett, Lost Letters, Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Commercialization of Club, Correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Criticism and Complaints, 1974 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Davy Crockett's Rifle, Correspondence, 1904 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Foundation and Corporation Involvement, Member Mailer Response Forms, 1991 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - General Correspondence, 1891 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - General Correspondence, 1893 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - General Correspondence, 1894 (Box-folder 2/13)